[
    {
        "question": "The wavelength of Micro waves is between .............. and ...............",
        "options": [
            "0.3 mm and 20 cm",
            "400 nm and 800 nm",
            "800 nm and 0.3 mm",
            "300 pm and 400 nm"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "The biggest optical telescope in India is situated at ...............",
        "options": [
            "Bengaluru",
            "Pune",
            "Mumbai",
            "Nainital"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "question": "Out of the following ............... is a telescope",
        "options": [
            "INSAT",
            "GSAT",
            "EDUSAT",
            "GMRT"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "question": "The only light radiation that our eyes are capable to sense is ................",
        "options": [
            "X-rays",
            "Radio waves",
            "Visible rays",
            "Micro waves"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "The wavelength of Ultraviolet rays is between ...............",
        "options": [
            "3pm and 300pm",
            "400 nm and 800 nm",
            "800 nm and 0.3 mm",
            "300 pm and 400 nm"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "question": "The GMRT gives data equivalent to a telescope having a dish with diameter ...............",
        "options": [
            "20 m",
            "400 m",
            "25 km",
            "3 km"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "The National Aeronautics and Space Administration launched an X-ray telescope in space called ..............",
        "options": [
            "Hubble",
            "Chandra",
            "IRS",
            "Astrosat"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "GMRT is used for ............... waves.",
        "options": [
            "Radio",
            "Micro",
            "Ultraviolet",
            "Gamma"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "The wavelength of ............... rays are shorter than 3 pm.",
        "options": [
            "Radio",
            "Micro",
            "Ultraviolet",
            "Gamma"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "question": "The wavelength of ............... waves is between 0.3 mm and 20 cm.",
        "options": [
            "Radio",
            "Micro",
            "Ultraviolet",
            "Gamma"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "The wavelength of X-rays is between ............... and .............",
        "options": [
            "3pm and 300pm",
            "400 nm and 800 nm",
            "800 nm and 0.3 mm",
            "300 pm and 400 nm"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "INSAT and GSAT are the satellites used for ...............",
        "options": [
            "Telecommunication network, television broadcasting.",
            "Education",
            "Disaster management",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "Hubble satellite is orbiting at a height of ............... km earth.",
        "options": [
            "259",
            "958",
            "589",
            "859"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "The ............... satellite series is used for education.",
        "options": [
            "INSAT",
            "GSAT",
            "EDUSAT",
            "Astrosat"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "The ............... series of satellite is used for monitoring and management of natural resources as well as disaster management.",
        "options": [
            "INSAT",
            "GSAT",
            "IRS",
            "Astrosat"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "The wavelength of visible light is between ................",
        "options": [
            "0.3 mm and 20 cm.",
            "400 nm and 800 nm",
            "800 nm and 0.3 mm",
            "300 pm and 400 nm"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "The wavelength of Radio waves is longer than about ................",
        "options": [
            "20 cm",
            "400 nm",
            "0.3 mm",
            "300 pm"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "Hubble telescope has a diameter of ............... inches",
        "options": [
            "25",
            "94",
            "20",
            "3"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "The wavelength of Gamma rays is shorter than ...............",
        "options": [
            "20 cm",
            "400 nm",
            "0.3 pm",
            "3 pm"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "question": "The wavelength of Infrared waves is between .............",
        "options": [
            "0.3 mm and 20 cm",
            "400 nm and 800 nm",
            "800 nm and 0.3 mm",
            "700 nm and 0.3 nm"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "A telescope is used to observe ................",
        "options": [
            "Sky",
            "Clouds",
            "Space",
            "Weather"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "The first scientist to use a telescope for space observation was ...............",
        "options": [
            "Aryabhatt",
            "Chandra",
            "Galileo",
            "Astrosat"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    }
]